Guide to the Bettye Lane photographs, 1959-2007, bulk 1970s-1980s RL.00793
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- People, 1970-2007; 159 items
  - Veteran Feminists of America - group portrait, 1993; 1 items (Box 4)
    About 35 women and one man. Includes Jacqui Ceballos, Phyllis Chesler, and Flo Kennedy. The others are unidentified.
  - Wallace, Michelle, 1979; 1 items (Box 4)
  - Wattleton, Faye, 1992; 1 items (Box 4)
- Subjects, 1970-1995; 346 items
  Folders in this series contain a wide variety of photographs arranged in topical groups by Bettye Lane; their titles are taken from original headings. There are folders on men supporting women's rights, health and sexuality, lesbian and gay rights, opposition groups, politics, religion and spirituality, and images of slogans, advertisements, and sayings, and more.
  Each folder contains an original annotated inventory sheet listing image titles, dates, image id, and location, taken from the detailed information found on the backs of most photographs. In a few cases there is considerable overlap, such as between "Signs and Graffiti" and "Words," but rather than merging folders, the original arrangement has been preserved. Some prints were removed from original "miscellaneous" folders and added to these subject groups. Additional images with the same focus can be found in the Events series.
  - Anti-Choice and Anti-ERA, 1970-1978; 19 items (Box 4)
    Images in this series focus on opposition groups. Subjects include: Anti-Women's Rights at the Women's March, 1970 (1); Protesters at a NOW Conference - Houston, Texas, 1974 (2); Anti-ERA - Federal Plaza, New York City, 1974 (5); International Women's Year Conference - Albany, New York, 1977 (1); I.W.Y. Conference - Houston, Texas, 1977 (9); Anti-Planned Parenthood - New York City, 1978 (1). Additional images of opposition groups are found in the Opposition folder. Other photographs taken at these conferences are found in the Events series.
  - Health, 1972-1989; 11 items (Box 4)
    Images include: self-exam and self-help posters and demonstrations; menstrual extraction; press conferences on health issues; and conferences on Disability and Sexuality, and mid-life issues. Includes photos of Phyllis Chesler, Jane Porcino (editor of Hot Flash magazine), Lorraine Rothman (proponent of menstrual extraction), Barbara Seaman, Faith Siedenberg, and Gloria Steinem.
  - Lesbian Rights, 1971-1984; 44 items 2 folders (Box 4)
    Consists of a variety of photographs related to lesbian activists and gay rights marches and rallies. There are many images of marches, including Christopher Street marches and commemorations in New York City. Subjects include: Bella Abzug, Ted Kennedy, Jean O'Leary, and Eleanor Smeal at an event; the founders of the Lesbian Herstory Archives in their office, 1979; Jean O'Leary speaking at a conference; lesbian mothers; Black Lesbian Caucus members marching; lesbian couples in Central Park; and scenes from an NBC show, "Lesbian Lifestyles," shot in a NYC lesbian bar and the Gay Activist Alliance headquarters. Some images are of lesbian contingents at marches for women's rights. Locations include: New York City, Albany, N.Y., Washington, D.C., and Texas.
  - Men for Women's Rights, 1970-1994; 26 items (Box 4)
    The focus in these photographs is on men in the women's movement. Images include men's contingents participating in the Women's March for Equality - New York City, 1970-1980, and International Women's Year events. There are also images from pro-choice rallies, anti-pornography protests, NOW conferences, fathers' rights rallies, Hustler magazine protest, and a MAMA media conference. Additional images from these and related events are found in the Events series. Men featured in photographs include Warren Farrell and Herman Badillo.
  - Opposition, 1974-1977; 3 items (Box 4)
    Images of opponents to feminist causes are from the I.W.Y. Conference - Houston, Texas, 1977, and the NOW Conference in Houston, Texas, 1974. Additional prints from these conferences are in the Events series.
  - Politics, 1972-1976; 17 items (Box 4)
    Among the photographs are images from the Democratic National Convention - Miami, Florida, 1972; Women for McGovern, 1972; and the Democratic National Convention - New York City, 1976.
  - Poverty and Homelessness, 1972-1987; 15 items (Box 4)
    Arranged in date order. Photographs are images of homeless women, some of them mental patients, with the focus on the feminization of poverty. One image is of an anti-poverty rally in Washington, D.C., 1987. Locations include: Miami, New York City, and Houston.
  - Professional and Blue Collar Jobs, 1971-1988; 60 items 2 folders (Box 5)
    Arranged in rough date order. Consists of a wide variety of portraits of women at work, with a focus on pioneers in particular fields. Examples include the first female State Police officer, the first woman taxi driver in NYC, and the first female union welder. Other images show all-women construction and film crews. There is an emphasis on the media, with women in television and film production, and journalism. Significant media figures include: Barbara Koppel, Pat Collins, Charlotte Curtis, and Marlene Sanders. Almost all the images were taken in New York City, but there is a group taken in New Mexico and one each from Houston, Mexico City, and Miami.
  - Professions, 1972-1995; 39 items 2 folders (Box 5)
    Arranged in rough date order. The main focus is on women in professions traditionally exclusive to men. Includes entries related to armed forces, business women, media professions, construction trades, and transportation. Many of the women pictured are African American.
  - Religion and Spirituality, 1974-1984; 13 items (Box 5)
    Arranged in date order. Images are chiefly from protests for women's ordination, religious women for peace, and an Earth Festival gathering. Significant individuals include theologian Mary Daly and activist Gloria Steinem, speaking at a Unitarian women's meeting in New York City, 1974. There is also an image of Cristo's female crucifixion.
  - Signs and Graffiti, 1970-1983; 7 items (Box 5)
    Features sexism in advertising for White Horse Scotch, a male club in New York, and feminist responses (a poster with a woman marked with cuts of beef, a union woman carrying a "Know women's history, we were always there" sign, and the slogans "Sexism is a social disease" and "A woman without a man is like a fish without a bicycle").
  - Women in Sports, 1972-1984; 58 items 2 folders (Box 5)
    Each folder is in separate date order. The first folder shows ordinary women in sports; the emphasis in the second grouping is on famous women athletes. They include: Cat Davis (2); Mary Decker; Jean Balukis; Mikki Gorman; Janet Guthrie; Billie Jean King (5); Nancy Lopez; Martina Navratilova; Ann Phillips; Karen Rogers (4); Jackie Tonawanda; and Wilma Rudolph. Locations include New York City, New Jersey, and California. A few images are in color. There are also a few general images in the second folder of female officials and coaches, the first professional women's rodeo, little league players, and roller derbies.
  - Words, 1970-1992; 34 items (Box 5)
    Images in this folder illustrate the sayings and slogans of the day, and how they were presented and distributed. The first 10 prints are color compilations of banners from Feminist newspapers, magazines, and organizations, then there are several color compilations of buttons. Individuals in photos are march attendees and vendors. Some show sexist advertising and feminist reactions. Several images are of bulletin boards or walls with signs, notices, and inspirational thoughts.